In the Taiwan-Korea semiconductor battle
who will be the last one standing?
Since the founding of TSMC
its greatest competitor has always been
another semiconductor giant—
Samsung from South Korea
In 1984
Samsung began producing 64Kb DRAM for Intel
By 1987
Samsung had already developed
cutting-edge, high-quality
4Mb DRAM--
the same year that TSMC was founded
The first generation Apple iPhone chips
were exclusively manufactured by Samsung
Even though they were fierce rivals in the smartphone market
TSMC and Samsung waged an all-out war after the millennium
How did TSMC break the deadlock?
Has TSMC really won
a decisive victory?
We mentioned in the last episode
that Sun Yun-suan, Li Kwoh-ting, and Morris Chang
worked together to promote the development of TSMC
embedding Taiwan
at the core of the global technology industry
We must say
Sun Yun-suan and Li Kwoh-ting had a keen eye for talent
They found the optimal position for Taiwan
from both economic and political perspectives
in the 1960s
Politically
from 1960 to the early 1970s
the U.S. was deeply entangled in the Vietnam war
in 1964
China conducted its first nuclear test.
President Chiang Kai-Shek of Taiwan at that time
was contemplating the Project Guoguang
secretly aiming to reclaim the Chinese mainland
Asia was far from stabe
The U.S. desperately needed an ally
for long-term collaboration in Southeast Asia.
The sisal hemp factory operated by veterans in Gangshan
was one of Taiwan’s emerging industries
It utilized Taiwan’s abundant sisal hemp supply
braiding it into ropes
for both domestic and international ships.
Economically
in the 1960s
Taiwan was actively promoting
labor-intensive export industries
The import substitution policy of the previous decade
transformed Taiwan from an agricultural economy to an industrial one
resulting in massive productive capacity
which at times seemed excessive for the domestic market.
So
in the 1960s, the policy shifted toward export orientation
attracting investments from advanced industrial countries
with its abundant supply of cheap labor
to help mitigate domestic issues caused by soaring wages
The governmentset up many Export Processing Zones
for light industries like appliances, textiles & plastics
The timing was perfect—
if Morris Chang of TI could be recruited
to launch semiconductor industry in Taiwan
The right time, place and people would be aligned
As Korea, Singapore, and Malaysia
entered the semiconductor competition one after another
Taiwan was ready to join as well
But the challenge for TSMC has just begun
TSMC was founded in 1987
and went public on the Taiwan Stock Exchange in 1994
As operations stabilized
the next challenge was
competing with other manufacturers
such as Samsung and Intel
In this market
competition was not only about production capacity
but also about who could make smaller transistors
and pack them into a chip
Yet as transistors shrank
new problemsemerged
Let’s review
A transistor functions like a small water valve
thatforms complex logic circuits
through a series of on-and-off switches.
The small water valve in a transistor
is called a “gate”, similar to a water gate
The inlet and outlet pipes
are called the “source” and “drain”
The source and drain are like
two reservoirs at the upstream and downstream ends of a river
To move water from the source to the drain
the water valve controlled by the gate must be opened
Among them
in the most popular transistor structure used in logic chips
the gate has a sandwich-like structure
composed of metal, an insulating oxide layer
and semiconductor material
Transistors of this type
are commonly known as MOSFETs
A single transistor structure
But TSMC can now fit 200 billion tiny transistors like this
in a single chip
This number is expected to surpass a trillion soon
How?
Obviously
the only way is to further shrink transistors
But as transistors shrink
the first challenge they face is
water valve leakage
Usually
the water valves in transistors
are designed to shut tightly
to resist horizontal hydraulic pressure
namely the vertical electric field applied to the gate
must be far stronger than horizontal field between the source and drain
If a closed water valve
fails to completely stop current flow
water spills over
leading to increased power consumption
Your smartphone would always need  to be connected to a power bank
or worse, the water valve could fail entirely
causing a total breakdown
The entire transistor becomes invalid
As transistors shrink
the driving voltage used in circuits
remained at about 0.7 volts
It means the valve is getting smaller
while the hydraulic pressure stays the same
The valve ends up
unable to stop leakage
caused by overflow current
And it’s not just leakage--
When the source and drain get closer
various short-channel effects happen
just like elderly folks
develop more chronic diseases over time
including velocity saturation
parasitic BJT
hot carrier effects
and threshold voltage roll-off, among others.
Engineers struggled to keep up
just like doctors watching red figures on a health report
For the miniaturization limit of transistors
have we found a solution?
To address the chronic disease called short channel effects
academia and industry have worked together
proposing various methods to keep Moore’s Law going
For example, semiconductor materials are modified
by doping silicon with other elements
To suppress leakage precisely
materials experts experimented with mixing different elements
at specific locations within transistors
much like knitting a wool blanket
placing fibers of different colors
in designated areas
The technique is called ion implantation
Who would have thought that semiconductors
could draw inspiration from handicraft?
Another approach was
to thin the insulation oxide layer in transistors
making it easier for the vertical electric field to pass through the gate channel
thereby enhancing control over the water valve
However
when the insulation layer becomes thinner than 5 nanometers
gate leakage starts
due to quantum tunneling effects
Though this solved the horizontal leakage issue
the valve that was supposed to block current flow
wow
now starts leaking itself
To solve this problem
Intel chose to change the insulationmaterial
at the node of 45 nanometers process
from silicon dioxide
to hafnium oxide which has a higher dielectric constant
This significantly reduced gate leakage
The tech was quickly adopted by semiconductor companies
and remains a key innovation till now
Even with such efforts
as transistors keep shrinking
to the node about 20 nanometers
these solutions began to wane
And too much mixing
not only made the process more complicated
but also lowered unit efficacy
Ultimately the breakthrough came
with an entirely new transistor structure
the Fin Field-Effect Transistor
or FinFET for short
The original structure of transistors
can be visualized as a 2D flat
The source and drain
were semiconductor materials embedded on a flat substrate
The gate applied voltage from above
meaning
the gate could onlyshut vertically downwards
As channels became shorter
the gate could no longer shut tightly
That’s when Masaru Hisamoto from Hitachi central research lab
had a groundbreaking idea
If we change the shape and structure of the electrodes
the gate could be shut from three directions simultaneously
This means transforming planar electrodes
into vertical fin-like structures
with the gate straddling the standing channel
As a result
the gate can touch the channel
from above and on both sides
forming a 3-sided gate
When we need to shut the gate
the gate’s electric field can block the channel effectively
from 3 directions
The gate in this MOSFET structure
is still metal
Insulating oxide layer
and semiconductor
The metal gate and thin oxide layer
clamp the fin-shaped channel
which connects the source and drain
The fin-shaped 3D design
was later commonly referred as FinFET
At that time
Masaru Hisamoto was conducting research
with a team at UC Berkeley
Prof. Chenming Hu,
a graduate of NTU’s Engineering dept.
was teaching at UC Berkeley
and happened to be a member of the team
According to Hisamoto’s memoir
the name FinFET
was Prof. Hu’s idea
Prof. Hu’s research team
introduced the concept in 1998
with a 17-nanometer FinFET
successfully overcoming the limitations of chip miniaturization
FinFET
can shut the gate tightly
even in extremely short channels
A shorter channel means a faster switching speed
and the voltage needed
to operate the gate
is lower
It saves more power
Furthermore
the 3D structure enabled transistors
to develop vertically
Designers could use the space above the chip
more efficiently
FinFET
had advantages in both performance and area efficiency
rapidly gaining traction in the global chip industry
hence started the dominating decade of FinFET
Since 2014
most of the process under 17 nanometers
have adopted the FinFET design
even with 5 and 3 nanometers production
in recent years
TSMC
is still following the same fin-based framework
TSMC rapid rise during this period
was partially due to its unique advantage in FinFET technology
In 2001, Prof. Hu was invited
by TSMC’s President Morris Chang
to return to Taiwan
as TSMC’s first Chief Technology Officer
bringing the latest FinFET tech to Taiwan
TSMC and Samsung
were locked in fierce competitionin the chip war
Since the first generation of Apple’s iPhone chips
were all exclusively mass-produced
by Samsung
However, Samsung was different from TSMC
They didn’t just make chips
but also design chips by themselves
Apple was surprised to find out
Samsung released its own S5PC100 processor
which used the same core as the A4 chip
for the iPhone 4
which Apple had authorized Samsung to produce
Moreover
Samsung’s Galaxy smartphones and tablets
was suspected of copying iPhone and iPad
It’s not acceptable
Eventually Apple and Samsung broke up
On April 15, 2011
Apple sued Samsung
for infringement litigation
at the Federal district court in San Jose,California
The lawsuit lasted for 7 years
Samsung ultimately compensated Apple $539 million
and the case endedin a settlement
Surely TSMC didn’t miss the opportunity
In the beginning Morris Chang decided
TSMC would only do ODM without IC design
The strategy has paid off
Since TSMC doesn’t produce chips under its own brand
Nobody worried about
TSMC plagiarizing their IC designs
Besides
the yield of TSMC’s 20 nanometers process
was best of the world
When Apple released iPhone 6
all orders for A8 chips
went to TSMC
You think this means
TSMC has won a total victory?
Nope
the chips a generation later
suddenly reversed the game
Prof. Hu’s student Liang Mong-Song
defected to Samsung
He helped Samsung surpass TSMC for half a year
by launching the FinFET process
at the 14-nanometer node, smaller than 20 nanometers
the A9 chips Apple released in 2015
were co-produced by Samsung and TSMC
It’s the ultimate showdown
Now, a decade after the duel
The era of FinFET is coming to an end
Major players like TSMC, Samsung and Intel
are all preparing for
the post-FinFET era
A whole new battlefield for chips has emerged
What will next-gen transistors look like?
How do TSMC stay ahead?
Please stay tuned to our channel
See you next time